Guide to the Bennett Cerf Papers
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Bennett Cerf Papers
ca. 1898-1977.
Cerf, Bennett, 1898-1971.
52 linear ft (ca. 6,300 items in 71 boxes, 45 volumes, & 22 oversized items).
Columbia University Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Butler Library, New York, NY 10027.
4079659
History
Author & publisher. Columbia A.B. 1919; Litt.B. 1920.
Scope and Content
Correspondence, manuscripts, memorabilia, photographs, phonograph and tape recordings, and printed files. Included are Cerf's personal correspondence files, 1929-1945, and the diaries and scrapbooks which he maintained from his school days throughout his active career. The diaries, in date-book format, contain terse notes on Cerf's meetings with authors and friends, on his travels and publishing activities; the scrapbooks contain correspondence and photographs, as well as memorabilia and printed items, and were annotated by Cerf and his wife, Phyllis Fraser Cerf Wagner. Also in the collection are manuscripts and proofs for Cerf's books including "The Laugh's on Me", "Treasury of Atrocious Puns", "The Sound of Laughter", "Stories to Make You Feel Better", and "At Random: the Reminiscences of Bennett Cerf", which was edited by Phyllis Cerf Wagner and Albert Erskine, 1977. The papers also include condolence letters written at the time of Cerf's death, photographs and photo albums,certificates and awards, and miscellaneous printed material, including Random House and Modern Library catalogues. Among the major correspondents are: Truman Capote, Dwight D. Eisenhower, Edna Ferber, Moss Hart, J. Edgar Hoover, Hubert Humphrey, Lyndon B. Johnson, John Lindsay, Joshua Logan, John O'Hara, Jacqueline Onassis, Richard Rodgers, Franklin D. Roosevelt, Gertrude Stein, Adlai Stevenson, Harry Truman, and Robert Penn Warren.
Arrangement
Selected materials cataloged; remainder arranged.
Subjects
Random House (Firm); Adams, Samuel Hopkins, 1871-1958.; Annenberg, Walter H., 1908-2002.; Astaire, Fred.; Auchincloss, Louis.; Baldwin, Faith, 1893-1978.; Baruch, Bernard M. (Bernard Mannes), 1870-1965.; Baxter, Anne.; Benny, Jack, 1894-1974.; Berlin, Irving, 1888-1989.; Bliven, Bruce, 1916-2002.; Bow, Clara, 1905-1965.; Bradley, Omar Nelson, 1893-1981.; Cabell, James Branch, 1879-1958.; Canfield, Cass, 1897-1986.; Capote, Truman, 1924-1984.; Cerf, Christopher.; Cooke, Alistair, 1908-2004.; Cousins, Norman.; Dewey, Thomas E. (Thomas Edmund), 1902-1971.; Dreiser, Theodore, 1871-1945.; Eban, Abba Solomon, 1915-2002.; Fadiman, Clifton, 1904-1999.; Faulkner, William, 1897-1962.; Ferber, Edna, 1887-1968.; Fisher, Dorothy Canfield, 1879-1958.; Flower, Des, omd, 1907-3-; Fontaine, Joan, 1917-; Gershwin, George, 1898-1937.; Gershwin, Ira, 1896-1983.; Gingrich, Arnold.; Goldwyn, Samuel, 1926-; Green, Martyn, 1899-1975.; Gruening, Ernest, 1887-1974.; Harriman, W. Averell (William Averell), 1891-1986.; Hart, Moss, 1904-1961.; Hemingway, Ernest, 1899-1961.; Hersey, John, 1914-1993.; Hitchcock, Alfred, 1899-1980.; Hoover, J. Edgar (John Edgar), 1895-1972.; Humphrey, Hubert H. (Hubert Horatio), 1911-1978.; Hurlock, Madeline, 1899-1989.; Huxley, Aldous, 1894-1963.; Ingersoll, Ralph, 1900-1985.; Javits, Jacob K. (Jacob Koppel), 1904-1986.; Johnson, Lyndon B. (Lyndon Baines), 1908-1973.; Jones, James, 1921-1977.; Jovanovich, William.; Kennedy, Edward Moore, 1932-; Kent, Rockwell, 1882-1971.; Kerr, Jean.; Knopf, Alfred A., 1892-1984.; Koch, Ed, 1924-; Kollek, Teddy, 1911-2007.; Lefkowitz, Louis J.; Lindsay, John V. (John Vliet); Logan, Joshua.; Loos, Anita, 1893-1981.; McBride, Mary Margaret, 1899-1976.; McFee, William, 1881-; Machen, Arthur, 1863-1947.; McKuen, Rod.; Malraux, André, 1901-1976.; Maugham, W. Somerset (William Somerset), 1874-1965.; Mencken, H. L. (Henry Louis), 1880-1956.; Merrick, David.; Michener, James A. (James Albert), 1907-1997.; Morley, Christopher, 1890-1957.; Nash, Ogden, 1902-1971.; Nathan, George Jean, 1882-1958.; O'Flaherty, Liam, 1896-1984.; O'Hara, John, 1905-1970.; Onassis, Jacqueline Kennedy, 1929-1994.; Paley, William S. (William Samuel), 1901-; Robinson, Edwin Arlington, 1869-1935.; Rodgers, Richard, 1902-1979.; Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich), 1908-1979.; Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945.; Roth, Philip.; Rusk, Dean, 1909-1994.; Russell, Rosalind.; Schiff, Dorothy, 1903-1989.; Schlesinger, Arthur M. (Arthur Meier), 1917-2007.; Schulberg, Budd.; Sevareid, Eric, 1912-1992.; Shaw, Irwin, 1913-1984.; Slesinger, Tess, 1905-1945.; Stein, Gertrude, 1874-1946.; Steinbeck, John, 1902-1968.; Stevenson, Adlai E. (Adlai Ewing), 1900-1965.; Styron, William, 1925-2006.; Tracy, Honor, 1915-; Truman, Harry S., 1884-1972.; Updike, John.; Van Vechten, Carl, 1880-1964.; Wagner, Phyllis Cerf, 1915-2006.; Wallace, Henry A. (Henry Agard), 1888-1965.; Warren, Robert Penn, 1905-1989.; Weidman, Jerome, 1913-1998.; White, E. B. (Elwyn Brooks), 1899-1985.; Wiesel, Elie, 1928-; Williams, G. Mennen, 1911-1988.; Willkie, Wendell L. (Wendell Lewis), 1892-1944.; Woollcott, Alexander, 1887-1943.; Wynn, Ed, 1886-1966.; Editors.; Literature.; Publishers and publishing.; Albums.; Articles.; Audio cassettes.; Awards.; Bookplates.; Certificates.; Diaries.; Illustrations.; Lectures.; Memoires.; Notebooks.; Passports.; Phonodiscs.; Photographs.; Proofs.; Scrapbooks.; Speeches.; Tape recordings.; Authors, American.
Access Restrictions
This collection has no restrictions.
The following boxes are located off-site: Boxes 3-75. You will need to request this material at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
Acquisition
1975 M-1975 Wagner, Phyllis Cerf Gift
10/09/1998 M-98-10-09 12 letters to & from M.H. Sherwood 2293B Purchase
Gift of Phyllis Cerf Wagner and the Cerf Foundation, 1975, 1978-1981 (yearly), 1983, & 1984; Gift of Random House, 1988.
Finding aid in repository and online.
- Series I: Cataloged Correspondence
  - Adams, Samuel Hopkins (Box 1)
  - Addams, Charles (Box 1)
  - Anderson. Robert (Box 1)
  - Annenberg, Walter (Box 1)
  - Astaire, Fred (Box 1)
  - Auchincloss, Louis (Box 1)
  - Baldwin, Faith (Box 1)
  - Baruch, Bernard M. (Box 1)
  - Baskerville, Charles (Box 1)
  - Baxter, Anne (Box 1)
  - Beer, Thomas (Box 1)
  - Benny, Jack (Box 1)
  - Berlin, Irving (Box 1)
  - Black, Hugo L. (Box 1)
  - Bliven, Bruce (Box 1)
  - Bow, Clara (Box 1)
  - Bradley, Omar N (Box 1)
  - Cabell, James Branch (Box 1)
  - Canby, Henry Seidel (Box 1)
  - Canfield, Cass (Box 1)
  - Capote, Truman (Box 1)
  - Cerf, Bennett A. (Box 1)
  - Cerf, Christopher (Box 1)
  - Cerf, Jonathan (Box 1)
  - Cooke, Alistair (Box 1)
  - Coppard, A. E. (Box 1)
  - Cousins, Norman (Box 1)
  - Crawford, Joan (Box 1)
  - Darrow, Whitney, Jr. (Box 1)
  - Dewey, Thomas E. (Box 1)
  - Douglas, Norman (Box 1)
  - Dreiser, Theodore (Box 1)
  - Early, Stephen (Box 1)
  - Eban, Abba (Box 1)
  - Eisenhower, Dwight David (Box 1)
  - Ervine, St. John (Box 1)
  - Fadiman, Clifton (Box 1)
  - Farley, Walter (Box 1)
  - Farrar, John (Box 1)
  - Faulkner, Estelle (Mrs. William) (Box 1)
  - Faulkner, William (Box 1)
  - Ferber, Edna (Box 1)
  - Fisher, Dorothy Canfield (Box 1)
  - Flower, Desmond. (Box 1)
  - Fontaine, Joan (Box 1)
  - Furness, Betty (Box 1)
  - Geisel, Theodor Seuss (Box 1)
  - Gershwin, George (Box 1)
  - Gershwin, Ira (Box 1)
  - Gingrich, Arnold (Box 1)
  - Goldwyn, Samuel, Jr. (Box 1)
  - Goodson, Mark (Box 1)
  - Grace, Princess of Monaco (Box 1)
  - Green, Martyn (Box 1)
  - Gruening, Ernest (Box 1)
  - Harcourt, Alfred (Box 1)
  - Harriman, William Averell (Box 1)
  - Hart, Moss (Box 1)
  - Hemingway, Ernest (Box 1)
  - Hersey, John (Box 1)
  - Hitchcock, Alfred (Box 1)
  - Hobson, Laura (Box 1)
  - Hogan, Frank Smithwick (Box 1)
  - Hoover, John Edgar (Box 1)
  - Humphrey, Hubert Horatio (Box 1)
  - Huxley, Aldous L. (Box 1)
  - Ingersoll, Ralph (Box 2)
  - Javits, Jacob K. (Box 2)
  - Johnson, Claudia Alta Taylor (Mrs. L.B.) (Box 2)
  - Johnson, Lyndon Baines (Box 2)
  - Jones, James (Box 2)
  - Jovanovich, William (Box 2)
  - Kraing, Kenneth B. (Box 2)
  - Kennedy, Edward M. (Box 2)
  - Kent, Rockwell (Box 2)
  - Kerr, Jean (Box 2)
  - Kiplinger, Willard Monroe (Box 2)
  - Knopf, Alfred A. (Box 2)
  - Knopf, Helen (Box 2)
  - Kober, Arthur (Box 2)
  - Koch, Edward I. (Box 2)
  - Kollek, Theodore (Box 2)
  - Lefkowitz, Louis J. (Box 2)
  - Lindsay, John Vliet (Box 2)
  - Lindsay, Mary (Mrs. John V.) (Box 2)
  - Logan, Joshua (Box 2)
  - Loos, Anita (Box 2)
  - McBride, Mary Margaret (Box 2)
  - McFee, William (Box 2)
  - McGovern, George (Box 2)
  - Machen, Arthur (Box 2)
  - McKuen, Rod (Box 2)
  - Malraux, André (Box 2)
  - Maugham, William Somerset (Box 2)
  - Mencken, Henry Louis (Box 2)
  - Merrick, David (Box 2)
  - Michener, James A. (Box 2)
  - Morley, Christopher (Box 2)
  - Nash, Ogden (Box 2)
  - Nathan, George Jean (Box 2)
  - O'Flaherty, Liam (Box 2)
  - O'Hara, John (Box 2)
  - Onassis, Jacqueline Bouvier Kennedy (Box 2)
  - Paley, William S. (Box 2)
  - Robinson, Edwin Arlington (Box 2)
  - Rockefeller, Margaretta F.M. (Mrs. N.A.) (Box 2)
  - Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Box 2)
  - Rodgers, Dorothy (Mrs. Richard) (Box 2)
  - Rodgers, Richard (Box 2)
  - Roosevelt, Franklin Delano (Box 2)
  - Roth, Philip (Box 2)
  - Rusk, Dean (Box 2)
  - Russell, Rosalind (Box 2)
  - Schiff, Dorothy (Box 2)
  - Schlesinger, Arthur M., Jr. (Box 2)
  - Schulberg, Budd (Box 2)
  - Sevareid, Eric (Box 2)
  - Shaw, Irwin (Box 2)
  - Sherwood, M.H.C. (Box 2)
  - Simon, Richard L. (Box 2)
  - Slesinger, Tess (Box 2)
  - Stein, Gertrude (Box 2)
  - Steinbeck, John (Box 2)
  - Stettinius, Edward R., Jr. (Box 2)
  - Stevenson, Adlai E. (Box 2)
  - Styron, William and Rose (Box 2)
  - Sulzberger, Arthur Ochs (Box 2)
  - Tracy, Honor (Box 2)
  - Truman, Harry S. (Box 2)
  - Tunney, James Joseph (Box 2)
  - Updike, John (Box 2)
  - Van Vechten, Carl (Box 2)
  - Wagner, Phyllis F.C. (Box 2)
  - Wallace, Henry Agard (Box 2)
  - Warren, Robert Penn (Box 2)
  - Weidman, Jerome (Box 2)
  - White, Elwyn Brooks (Box 2)
  - Wiesel, Elie (Box 2)
  - Williams, G. Mennen (Box 2)
  - Willkie, Wendell L. (Box 2)
  - Woollcott, Alexander (Box 2)
  - Wynn, Ed (Box 2)
- Series II: Cataloged Manuscripts, Photographs, and Art
  - Benson, Sally (Box 2)
  - Cerf, Bennett A (Box 2)
  - Clegg, Ernest (Box 2)
  - Dwiggins, William Addison (Box 2)
  - Ellis, Havelock (Box 2)
  - Furness, Betty (Box 2)
  - Geisel, Theodor Seuss (Box 2)
  - Gooden, Stephen (Box 2)
  - Haas, Robert (Box 2)
  - Hollister, Paul (Box 2)
  - Hoover, John Edgar (Box 2)
  - Kent, Rockwell (Box 2)
  - Lawrence, David Herbert (Box 2)
  - Leighton, Clare (Box 2)
  - Lindsay, Howard (Box 2)
  - Losch, Tilly (Box 2)
  - McFee, William (Box 2)
  - Mdrley, Christopher (Box 2)
  - Richards, Ceri (Box 2)
  - Robinson, Edwin Arlington (Box 2)
  - Shaw,George Bernard (Box 2)
  - Sinatra, Frank (Box 2)
  - Stephens, James (Box 2)
  - Stevenson, Adlai (Box 2)
  - Van Loon, Hendrik Willem (Box 2)
  - Van Vechten, Carl (Box 2)
  - Weston, Edward (Box 2)
  - Woolsey, John Munro (Box 2)
- Series III: Arranged Materials
  - Articles and speeches by Cerf--A-Z (Box 25)
  - Audio Records
    - "November 22" (Box 74)
    - "Frank Sinatra: A Man and His Music" (Box 74)
      (Limited Edition)
    - "Let’s Talk About Writers with Bennett Cerf" (Box 74)
  - Clippings Books
    - 1916-1917 (Box 36)
    - 1917-1919 (Box 36)
    - 1918-1933 (Box 36)
  - Condolence Letters
    - Record of Letters, (1 Volume)
      - A-D (Box 8)
      - E-L (Box 9)
      - M-Z (Box 10)
    - Condolence Message from Random House, Inc. concerning the death of Bennett Cerf (Box 64)
  - Interview--B. Cerf Interviewed by Arnold Michaelis, WOR-TV, 1963 June 20 (Box 25)
    (Audio Cassette)
  - Lecture Schedules, 1949-1971 (Box 31)
  - Manuscripts and Proofs
    - Diaries
      - 1915-1949 (Box 11)
      - 1950-1971 (Box 12)
    - Notebooks and Passports (Box 12)
    - The Laugh’s on Me (Box 13-14)
    - Treasury of Atrocious Puns (Box 14)
    - The Sound of Laughter (Box 15-17)
    - Stories to Make You Feel Better (Box 18)
    - At Random
      - Typed Manuscript (t.ms.) (Box 19-20)
      - Typed Manuscript (t.ms.)
        - Cuts and Discards (Box 21)
        - List of Illustrations (Box 21)
        - Index (Box 21)
        - Typesetters copy of typed manuscript (t.ms.) (Box 21)
        - 1st Draft (Box 21a)
      - Uncorrected 1st Proof (Box 21a)
      - Master Galley (Box 22)
      - Master Page Proofs (Box 22)
      - Page Proofs (foul matter) (Box 22)
      - Photographs and Illustrations for the Book (Box 22)
      - Correspondence (Box 23)
      - Reviews and Related Material (Box 23)
      - Mock-Ups (Box 63)
    - Try and Stop Me (Box 24)
    - Cerfboard (Box 24)
    - Vest Pocket of Anecdotes (Box 24)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 64)
  - Memorabilia and Miscellaneous Items (Box 35)
  - Oral History Memoir, Columbia University (Box 26-28)
    [This material has been withdrawn from this collection and returned to the Columbia University Center for Oral History.]
  - Personal Papers
    - 1926 1929-1933 (Box 3)
    - 1936-1940 (Box 4)
    - 1941-1943 (Box 5)
    - 1943-1945 (Box 6)
    - 1947-1971 undated (Box 7)
  - Photographs
    - Photographs of Cerf (Box 32)
    - Photographs of Bennett Cerf, Phyllis Cerf, Gustave Cerf, Cerf family, and miscellaneous (Box 33)
    - Photographs and photograph albums (Box 34)
      (Primarily Cerf, family, and friends; 1981 and 1984 additions to the collection)
    - Photograph Albums (Box 75)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 64)
  - Printed Material
    - About Cerf (Box 39)
    - Articles by Cerf (Box 40-41)
    - Bookplates of Bennett Cerf (Box 62)
    - Books by Cerf (Box 42-47)
    - Books by Phyllis Cerf Wagner (Box 48)
    - Books from the Library of Bennett Cerf (Box 49-55)
    - Columbia University; Miscellaneous (Box 61)
    - Inscribed Copy of The Look Book (Box 75)
    - Inscribed Copy of Salt Air (Box 75)
    - Leighton, Clare, The Return of the Native, 1929 (Box 63)
    - Woodcuts; one of 30 numbered sets of 12 prints, signed; illustrations for Thomas Hardy, The Return of the Native, (New York: Harper Brothers, 1929) (Box 63)
    - Musical Score for "Joanna" (Box 74)
      (Autographed by Rod McKuen)
    - Random House and Miscellaneous (Box 56)
    - Random House and Modern Library Catalogues (Box 57)
    - Random House Catalogues (Triplicate) (Box 58)
    - Random House Stock Information (Box 58)
    - Random House Printed Material (Box 59)
    - Random House Printed Material (duplicates) (Box 60)
  - Scrapbooks
    - 1933-1940 (Box 37)
    - 1940-1943 (Box 38)
    - 1944 January -October (Box 74)
    - 1944 November -1946 November (Box 65)
    - 1946 December -1949 June (Box 66)
    - 1949-1952 April (Box 67)
    - 1952 April -1954 December (Box 68)
    - 1955 January -1957 October (Box 69)
    - 1957 October -1960 July (Box 70)
    - 1960 July -1964 April (Box 71)
    - 1964 April -1968 February (Box 72)
    - 1968 January -1971 (Box 73)
    - 1945-1970 (Box 74)
  - Wagner, Phyllis Cerf et al. Charlotte, Isabelle, Phyllis and Susan’s New York. New York. (Box 29-30)
- Series IV: Oversized Materials
  - Academic Gown (Box Flat Box 294)
  - Charcoal portrait of Bennett Cerf by René Bouchet (Box Flat Box 293)
  - Condolence message from Random House, Inc. concerning the death of Bennett Cerf (Box Flat Box 296)
  - Honorary Degree Awards (Box Flat Box 296)
  - Manuscripts and Proofs--At Random, the Reminiscences of Bennett A. Cerf, 1977 (Box Flat Box 295)
    (Page proofs, photographs, end-paper)
  - Photographs (Oversized)
    - Bennett Cerf in front of the Random House building (photograph by Ray Shorr) (Box Flat Box 295)
    - Bennett Cerf with Marilyn Monroe (Box Flat Box 295)
    - Bennett Cerf in office (Box Flat Box 295)
    - Bennett Cerf in office with Secretary Paulene Kreeswork Freidnear (Box Flat Box 295)
    - Bennett Cerf at desk (Box Flat Box 295)
    - David Klopper, Robert Hoas, and Bennett Cerf (Box Flat Box 295)
    - Jonathan and Christopher Cerf (sons of Bennett and Phyllis Cerf) (Box Flat Box 295)
    - Other Miscellaneous Photographs (Box Flat Box 295)
    - Photograph of Bennett Cerf in office (Box Flat Box 293)
    - Bennett Cerf in office (Photograph by Ray Shorr) (Box Flat Box 296)
    - James Silverman, Robert Berstein, Bennett Cerf, and Lyndon Johnson (Box Flat Box 296)
    - Photograph of sign, "Sioux City Welcomes Bennett Cerf" (Box Flat Box 296)
    - Bennett Cerf in office with children’s books (Box Flat Box 296)
    - Bennett Cerf (as younger man) (Box Flat Box 296)
    - Other Miscellaneous Photographs (Box Flat Box 296)
    - John O’Hara (Photograph by Phyllis Cerf) (Box Flat Box 296)
  - Photostat reproduction of front page of "New York Times" 1898 May 25 (Box Flat Box 293)
  - Two mock-ups: cartoon sketches (Box Flat Box 294)